howdy this is gym rat and this is the
gym rat show
[Music]
today's guest is least small enough
physicist who was on the faculty of the
Perimeter Institute for Theoretical
Physics in Waterloo Ontario Lee could
you tell us a little bit about the
Perimeter Institute yes Jim and thank
you very much for inviting me
the friendlier Institute is a
public-private partnership that was
started by my class Regis who was one of
the founders of the founder of Research
In Motion that he was the inventor of
the smartphone and the BlackBerry if you
remember the blackberry
indeed he got this idea around 2000 that
he would like to do something for
science and he indeed was a big fan of
theoretical physics and he found himself
all of a sudden because it happened very
quickly
with wealth and the freedom to do
something dramatic for the sciences
theoretical physics that he was such a
fan of and indeed he's wanted to be a
scientist when he was growing up as a
poor immigrant to Canada and so he
discussed it with a number of people and
one of them was a very extraordinarily
resourceful just an extraordinary as I
don't know how to characterize him in
small bits I'm Howard burden who was
just getting his PhD then from the
University of Waterloo in quantum
gravity which is my field and Howard had
no administrative experience whatsoever
no experience in the Academy is anything
other than a student or a graduate
student but Mike saw something in him
which was a great vision and a great
leadership and picked Howard first to do
research about the shape of the new
Institute they're talking about and then
to actually be the first director that's
an amazing story that is an amazing
story and it still has to do with our
success as he stole very as the director
no he was the director until 2006 and
then he left and now lives in the South
of France where he has an interesting
life in me also I think is making pod
well life is good in the South of France
life is good in the South of France and
he's there with his family our second
director was Neil Turok
we just ended his ten-year to terms of
ten years and Howard put us on the map
and gave us a set of principles and
structure which was made us was quite
distinctive and different than all the
other sentence for theoretical physics
in the world and Neil then took that and
grew us by a factor of three into a
formidable Centre for research I'm
really glad that the BlackBerry guy did
that I mean that's a frankly a much
better use of money than yet another
200-foot yacht I would say yes no Mike
Mike is a person with vision a person
with enormous generosity and he his
initial contribution was a hundred
million dollars which was made as a kind
of challenge to the governments of
Canada to Ontario to match in that offer
of match has been made twice more than
that so his funding has been critical
but close so has been funding from the
province of Ontario and the Government
of Canada we have strong support from
the public from the governments and from
the private sector and that gives us so
formidable strength it gives us freedom
indeed and you know I've been associated
with the Santa Fe Institute for the last
17 years and it has a different
trajectory but a similar story and that
it's an independent standalone Institute
founded by a small group of visionaries
and has gone on to do some pretty
interesting things though not at the
scale in terms of at least headcount at
the Perimeter Institute anyway the
reason I asked Lee to be on our show
today was that I recently read one of
his books I've actually read several of
his books but just recently I read
Einsteins unfinished revolution the
search for what lies beyond the quantum
it examines what's often called quantum
foundations which examines the question
on what's really happening beyond what
our calculations tell us in the world of
the tiny where quantum mechanics reigns
this is an area I've been interested in
for
I'm the first thing I read on quantum
foundations it was a popular book by
Nick Herbert called quantum reality
which I probably read 30 years ago and I
that's when I recommend I don't know if
it's still very accurate but it was
certainly evocative and has got me
thinking I've been sort of following the
area outside of it the right corner of
my eye ever since so we're gonna talk
about quantum foundations but before we
do that Lee could you start with a
description of quantum mechanics it's
suitable for intelligent but not
necessarily scientifically trained
audience that's the audience I always
try to speak to Jim quantum mechanics is
the science of the atomic world of
radiation atoms nuclei molecules and so
forth
it was invented in the early part of the
20th century and is still I would claim
not yet in finished form quantum
mechanics is unusual as a physical
theory in that it seems to require that
we give up some of the intuitive or
seemingly obvious assumptions about
nature and our perception of it mainly
that what's true about the natural world
is independent of our beliefs or our
knowledge of it and this notion that
challenges the very idea of realism that
science it's about the real world does
this really is independent of our
dreaming about it imagining Astrid
knowledge of it is the key issue on
which the debates over the last 78 years
have turned and continued to turn very
interesting now one key question before
we get into foundations that I know
befuddled Suleyman and may even befuddle
some of the scientists studying the area
as to what degree does quantum mechanics
introduce true randomness into our world
you know the thought experiment I've
used to try to think about this is
suppose we had the thousand boxes with a
measured radioactive source that had a
mean decay rate of one hour we had a
Geiger counter in each box and each box
was associated with one of the top
thousand cities and population in the
world
and the first hundred to decay
dispatched an ICBM with a nuclear
warhead to detonate over that city kind
of a grisly example but is that process
of what hundred cities get destroyed
truly random whatever that really means
truly random means has no underlying
cause and according to quantum mechanics
as was formulated in the 1920s it is
indeed true randomness there is no cause
when there is a decay rate for a
radioactive atom which is the half-life
in the amount of time it will take half
of a population of them to decay but
which decays and when and what order is
according to the principles of quantum
mechanics entirely random now whether
that's really true whether it is a
hidden underlying cause it's just not
described so we have an incomplete
description of reality there's another
way to put the battleground that people
are fight over Einstein right off the
bat and a number of the other founders
in quantum mechanics like Rowan
Schrodinger and the way debry argue the
quantum mechanics was incomplete and
that it was hidden information or as
they came to be called hidden variables
that if we knew them would allow us to
predict exactly which atom with decay
when and the claim then is that quantum
mechanics is a kind of handy
approximation to the truth it doesn't
contain the whole truth great so that's
a great transition to the question of
quantum foundations right
quano foundations is the branch of
physics where we focus on these
fundamental questions about the nature
of reality and randomness and so forth
as relevant for the quantum domain could
you give us a brief review of what some
of those questions are and maybe some of
the specific leading interpretations
and why is there such disagreement about
what quantum mechanics means I mean you
know naively is a layman one thinks of
science as the world of things nailed
down mostly but you know these
discussions of quantum foundations range
very very widely as you know better than
almost anybody so if you could address
what some of these interpretations are
and why there's so much disagreement
still well I think the disagreement
because the options are limited and the
issues are quite profound and with it's
the kind of thing that we're deeply
interested in those of us who go into
science seriously whether a lay person
like yourself or those of us who get
trained as a professional scientists
have this interest because we care about
the nature of reality we want to tell a
story to our children and our
grandchildren about what the world is it
ultimately how we fit into it and the
fundamental laws of physics the
fundamental laws that shape the forces
that guide the elementary particles that
are the cause of atoms and molecules and
everything that were made of and so
forth is fundamental importance now the
way that quantum mechanics was
originally formulated in the early part
of the 20th century it was instigated by
Einstein and a few others by put into
final form in the 1920s by a number of
people Niels Bohr Werner Heisenberg are
two of the most prominent Wolfgang Pauli
Paul Dirac and English smitten there
were maybe half a dozen and these people
were philosophically not inclined to
realism for reasons of their own which
is interesting to explore so they
presented a theory in which randomness
was fundamental in which there was no
determinism and I can explain exactly
what it means why it lacks the idea the
things are determined as the future is
determined from the past and the present
and in the version of quantum mechanics
that they proposed the state of a system
does depend on what you choose to
measure and what's true about a system
does depend to some extent on what
questions us
system so there was a kind of
unification the way they saw it was
unity not in the usual sense of unifying
the different forces but in unity of
reality in the observer they saw the
reality is something that is created by
the observer as it tells the observer
finds out about it he also influences
and constructs reality and this was very
pleasing to those of that generation
they thought that they saw it as a as a
irrefutable and irreversible change and
revolutionary change in the idea of what
science is and how we relate to nature
and it was repellent to those who had
the older view that the world is
independent of our talking and thinking
about it ok so this was an anathema to
those who had the older more traditional
notion of reality is independent of our
knowledge and those included Einstein
Schrodinger Dubrow in a bunch of others
and so there are two groups would take a
widely different view and what they
prescribe is different basically when
you come to think about these questions
you face a question there's a kind of
branch in the road at the beginning of
your thinking do you think that quantum
mechanics is correct and the problem is
just how we think and talk about it
whether the basic equations of basic
predictions of quantum mechanics are
correct and complete and if you do then
you're interested in just having the
most elegant and useful language to
describe the strange new reality and
then you're interested in what's called
the interpretation of quantum mechanics
and as you hinted there are lots of
different interpretations and I can
outline some of them but that's only
path to subject if on the other hand you
think the quantum mechanics lacks the
full picture that it's incomplete then
you're looking for new knowledge about
nature to complete it new hypotheses
maybe new particles or new degrees of
freedom new forces and then you're a
functioning not like a philosopher
looking for
different interpretation the most
elegant way to say things but looking
for a different physical theory and
that's the work that I do I've certainly
aligned myself with that branch to the
subject and that was the part of the
surgery that was started by Einstein and
de Brian Schrodinger a question back to
the interpretations probably the
dominant interpretation since the
founding of the field Lee since it
coalesced is the so-called Copenhagen
interpretation could you tell our
audience about what that is and and I
realize it's not your interpretation but
at least to provide that background for
people so that they know what the
majority of the field has thought for
the majority of the time yes although I
should say there are very few pure
Copenhagen is left alive at this point
but they were the first they recalled
the Copenhagen interpretation because
Niels Bohr who was the first person who
successfully applied the ideas about
quantum physics to the island and
develop these ideas of energy levels and
orbitals and so forth so he was a very
important scientist for the development
to the theory and the Dutch government
in conjunction with a beer company
Carlsberg beer basically set him up in
an institute with secure funding and
beautiful building and a beautiful house
with a director lived and could
entertain visitors and this Center what
became the call that Niels Bohr
Institute became the creative Center for
the birth of quantum mechanics all of
the young people who played a key role
like Werner Heisenberg Wolfgang Pauli
and so forth were frequent visitors to
the center or were students or postdocs
there and so that's why this is the
ideas that they came up with are called
the Copenhagen interpretation now to
illustrate how they target and let me
emphasize this is a more radical point
of view than most people now think you
have to go to make sense of quantum
mechanics but it's very evocative and
it's a good place to start Niels Bohr
for example talked about the question of
whether the electron is a wave or a
particle
Einstein had shaken the world up and
this was the first intimations of
quantum physics in about 1905 when he
talked about light being both waves and
a particle and seeming to have aspects
of both
nature's and that's almost paradoxical
because the wave is something which is
spread out and flows through all the
available space open to it but as the
particle is always on a trajectory and
it's always somewhere and I was always
going somewhere so waves and particles
are quite different
what Bors said is that an electron or a
photon is neither a wave nor particle
these are the human invented conceptions
that we impose on not the particle but
the whole experiments we set up designed
to reveal the nature of the particle and
there are some experiments which are
naturally it's designed to bring out the
wave properties of a photon there are
the experiments which are designed to
bring out the particle properties so we
use these languages we choose which
language is most appropriate for the
whole experimental situation and we
demand only one thing a kind of
consistency which is if there's no
experiment that will lead us to try to
use the wave picture in the particle
picture at the same time and therefore
risk contradicting ourselves and this
style of thought that the world could be
fully described only by properties which
contradict each other if they were
forced to be used at the same time but
are sometimes used once a times use
another with what Neal's bar called
complementarity and he thought that he
had made a great philosophical discovery
in fact he thought he had gotten it from
the Bible from the mystic writings of
the Kabbalah and other religions he
talked about the couple of Eternity
between God's love and God's justice for
example God we teach loves each one of
us but God also has justice which is
strict according to the religious
teachings and how can God love us and be
a strict disciplinarian is a mystery is
a mystery
not just for God but I'd say as a parent
it's a mystery one thing our us laymen
often hear about the Copan
interpretation is the very shorthand
saying shut up and calculate that's not
really part of the Copenhagen
interpretation what happened the seven
calculate is from another generation of
scientists you see what happened is that
the generations and made quantum
mechanics like borign Heisenberg and
Einstein enterprise and Schrodinger and
all these people were a scientist of a
certain type they were deep thinkers and
they were very philosophically oriented
they were influenced by philosophy they
knew the history of philosophy they
would often be talking about what their
favorite philosophers whether it was
Leibniz or contour a Sorella would think
of these developments and they were very
therefore they oriented what they were
doing in the history of thought in the
history of philosophy then there came a
later generation people who were 10-15
years younger who just began their
studies when quantum mechanics was
invented and they weren't interested in
these philosophical discussions they
thought these philosophical discussions
for a waste of time and there was
instead so many opportunities to use the
new quantum mechanics to break open and
understanding of chemistry or nuclear
physics or solid-state physics or
astrophysics everything from how a
superconductor works to how starburns
energy was open season and it was an
extraordinary period this sort of from
the 1930s into the 1970s and during that
period pragmatism was a spouse and was
emphasized and people who would have
been more fitting of the earlier period
who came into science asking
philosophical questions
we're told that was no longer relevant
and to shut up and calculate well thank
you for that distinction that's a
historical distinction I was not aware
of can I give an example Freeman Dyson
is somebody you may have heard of the
bread he's a brilliant scientist and a
brilliant writer and there's just no
shortage of good things I could say
about Freedman I've also been blessed to
have met him I can always call him from
memory Freeman said about this that
usually it's the young people
revolutionaries and the older people who
are reactionaries but his generation
came in to science taught by an older
generation who were all revolutionaries
and who were all still engaged in these
philosophical arguments leftover from
the revolution they had made and so he
and his generation had to be different
and they had no choice but to be
reactionaries in to be pragmatic rather
than philosophical oh well it's
interesting those of us who are parents
sometimes see that pattered in our
children right that they react against
some of our structures and define
themselves in an alternative way so
that's something is that certainly makes
sense kind of from a human psychology
perspective let's get back to your
arguments in the book you argue for the
realist branch and you go into some of
the history of that could you you know
lay out where the realist branch came
from and who some of the leading people
are and you know where you see the
realist branch today
so the original realist was of course
Einstein and Einstein objected very
early on to the philosophical tone of
the writing of first niels bohr and then
the younger generation niels bohr Oh was
kind of halfway between Einstein and the
generation of Heisenberg just to paint
the picture Heisenberg and his friends
and colleagues were sort of born as of
the turn of the century so they just
missed being drafted into the first
world war and were in their early 20s
while quantum mechanics was being
developed in the middle late 20s and
only really one of those of that
generation was a realist and his name
was Louie de Blois and he was very
important universally admired because he
had taken the idea of the wave particle
duality of light Einstein has put
forward and said also an electron could
be sometimes away with sometimes a
particle with the same kind of mysteries
attendant and indeed anything all matter
I would have both wave and particle
properties and deploy through from those
ideas some predictions
the idea that you could diffract
electrons in a crystal the same way you
can defrag light and the this phenomenon
of electron diffraction was seen by some
Americans at Bell Labs in the early mid
1920s and that solidified the boy's
reputation and fame and indeed he not
too long after one Nobel Prize for that
crucial innovation but debris went on to
say what's the resolution of the puzzle
how do you from a realist point of view
avoid the idea of complementarity and
observer dependence and observer
intervention he said well let's suppose
that there are both waves and particles
and there's always a way then it flows
through the experiment taking all the
available paths and it's always a
particle which follows the way the wave
is known as a guidance wave and it
guides the particle and so this double
theory in which through both waves and
particles to probably developed and
proposed he called it the part of the
wave theory because the wave was a pilot
or a guide to the particle and
predictions and explanations which were
the equivalent to many cases in a few
cases better than those given by the
quantum mechanics that his colleagues
had developed so there was from the very
beginning of the subject a realist
alternative this pilot wave theory
Einstein had turned out had also come
upon that idea and it had written down a
pilot wave theory for photons which he
however found some problems with and got
discouraged and although he wrote a
paper about it it was doing it for
publication and he never presented it
and never much talked about it but
Einstein did also consider that
alternative so it's a kind of a mystery
for example in 1927 there was the first
conference which was held in Brussels
called the soul of a conference were all
the important people in quantum
mechanics got together for the first
time and gave talks to each other about
the new physics and debris was there and
I
was there and debris presented his part
of the way theory so there was no excuse
not to know about it that all the
founders must have been aware of it but
it was never taken up it was never
taught it was never made part of the
theory that was described in textbooks
it was as if he didn't exist in a
certain sense why was that do you think
well how do you think that his
pilot-wave theory was almost erased from
history it's a very interesting question
it's a question about history of science
and the sociology and psychology of
scientists which are not feels that I'm
expert in let me mention one part of it
a very important mathematician of that
day was somebody called John von Neumann
a Hungarian of that same generation and
indeed von Neumann did many important
things one of them was he invented the
standards computer architecture in the
1940s that all the computers used now
with memory separated from processing
for example with his innovation and but
he was a very important mathematician
all over the field of mathematics and
science and engineering this is how it
which is to say he was a very admired
and influential guy and in 1933 I
believe he published a book called the
mathematical principles of quantum
mechanics in which he gave a
mathematical proof that there could be
no alternative that a theory that was
more complete that filled in the missing
information than quantum mechanics would
have to be self contradictory or
disagree with the experiment and this
theorem was the impossibility proof as
it was called was very influential and
for the next twenty something years
whenever anybody would talk about why
can't there be a more complete
description somebody would say but just
for you you're naive you haven't studied
everything you have to study von
neumann's proof environment has proved
it's impossible now this is what's
really bizarre is that the boys
pilot-wave theory was a counterexample
to exclaim and by his very existence -
Bryce pilot-wave theory
showed
steerer must have been incorrect even I
fell for it even too bright
after the 1930s with tall people who
came to him said what about your pilot
wave theory he said well if I know him
and his truth that's impossible now
here's the really really interesting
part of the story there was a mistake
and by no means proof great
mathematician as he was he made mistakes
and there was a mistake in that truth
and there was a mathematics student
called Greta Hermann was doing a PhD in
the 1930s it was a friend of Heisenberg
and some of these other people she was
also a PhD student of Emmy Noether who
was a very important mathematician for
some work having to do with the role of
symmetry in physics so the way just to
say that thread of Hermann was a person
who was well situated in the center of
things and she took to heart the message
to study von neumann's theorem and she
studied it and she found there was a big
mistake at the center of it roughly
speaking he assumed what he was trying
to prove which is a way even very
talented people can mess up sometimes so
he was a great mathematician but his
proof was erroneous and proof that his
proof was erroneous was seen and worked
out by gradual men and published in
about 1935 there's sort of an obvious to
anybody anyway by this isn't surprise
pilot-wave theory there is an
alternative history and which people
read Greta Hermann and credited her and
began to work again on the pilot-wave
theory in the middle of 1930s that's not
what happened what happened is that it
took another physicist this one an
American called David Bohm to reinvent
the theory that is to price pilot-wave
theory which he did in the 1950s when he
was an assistant professor at Princeton
University when that there was a 20-year
gap perhaps more like a 30 year gap
between the two inventions amazing then
what happened when Bohm
refloated the idea was it accepted
rejected attacked a little bit of both
well
a little bit of both David Bohm was an
interesting person this was during the
McCarthy period of all the rabbit
anti-communism in the United States and
David Bohm liked his supervisor J robert
Oppenheimer and many of the people who
were around Oppenheimer had flirted with
communism in the 1920s and 1930s and as
a result this around the time he came up
with this new version of quantum
mechanics he was called before the House
Committee on an American activities and
he refused to testify and he was cited
and charged with contempt of Congress
which he was eventually acquitted of but
meanwhile Princeton did not renew his
contract and he as a result couldn't get
a job to continue as a physicist in the
United States and had to move to Brazil
where they were happy to welcome you
interesting in so that his rediscovery
of broglie's work then lead to a new
generation of realists it did eventually
but the reaction at the time was to
acknowledge that the theory existed and
is what it was he and dubrow's edited
but to ignore it that is a great quote
there are many good quotes of why people
talk themselves into thinking that the
best thing to do was just to ignore it
is irrelevant but indeed J robert
Oppenheimer who is had been his mentor
in thesis advisor and was then director
of the Institute for Advanced Study very
famously said if we can't disprove David
Bohm wrong we must all agree to ignore
his theory that's not very scientific
yes one wonders of course Oppenheimer
was a very good scientist but he also
had problems of his own with the
government at about that time and he had
good reason to perhaps want to distance
himself from David Bohm who was gonna be
more easily painted as a communist or
communist sympathizer the story is very
complicated and I started to look into
it but it wasn't my main intention I
would wanted to tell stories about
science help people understand the
scientific issues but I did not stop
myself as a biographer I think there is
great history of science in history in
general waiting to be written here just
one aspect of it let me leave as a hint
is that David Bohm and Einstein were
very friendly and most of that is
unrecorded but they seem to have had
some mutual friends in the area and to
have communicated through these mutual
friends and it was Einstein you see let
me go back a step why did David Bohm
come to invent this reinvent this
pilot-wave theory which gave a realist
perspective on quantum mechanics well it
wasn't his area he wasn't he was a
plasma physicist and the but he decided
to write a textbook on Harlan mechanics
because teaching quantum mechanics was
one of his duties at Princeton and he
was dissatisfied with the textbooks that
existed so he wrote a brilliant textbook
which is still used sometimes to this
day which gave a strict
defense of the Copenhagen point of view
and Einstein the legend goes called them
in Sora's textbook and called him in for
a discussion they were apparently
already so much friendly and Einstein
somehow gave him enough of a talking to
that it made David Bohm go back and
reconsider what he had written in
defense of the Copenhagen view and that
led directly to his playing around with
the equations and the principles and
reinventing the pilot wave theory Oh
within a few weeks so for his
conversation with Einstein by the way
just something else to go to starting
could looking to Freeman Dyson told me
that when David Bohm first came to
Princeton he and Freeman had dinner
together every night in the black side
of town which was forbidden explicitly
forbidden but by the rules of Robert
Oppenheimer for the fellows at the
Institute to go slumming as it were to
the black side of Princeton but because
of the eyes Ian Freeman went almost
every night together there's a bunch of
interesting personal stories as they're
all
is so why don't we start to move on to
what happened after a bomb and the
development of some of the scientific
theories in the realist branch well so
the key issue is if you're realist
what is the mystery about if it's not
about uncertainty because the pilot-wave
theory explains what's gonna happen and
resolves the problem about uncertainty
it's not about complementarity what is
the real mystery about and Einstein
again in this last paper about quantum
mechanics 1935 kind of almost
accidentally finds the key thing the key
thing is what we call now entanglement
contango and says there's two quantum
particles interact and then separate
when named they may go a long way from
each other
meters are lightyears then they share
properties in ways that can't be
attributed separately to either one of
them having a property and this is
entirely unlike the rest of science to
the rest of physics the idea the two
particles distantly separated but having
once interacted share properties which
cannot be attributed to either one
separately or any combination of
properties that either one separately
may have and this concept of
entanglement we understand now is what
makes quantum mechanics radically
different from the rest of physics
indeed all the exciting stuff going on
now such as he attempts to build quantum
computers which would be able to break
codes and do things that no normal
computer could do in the finite amount
of time or rely on this property of
entanglement and entanglement is now
something that the experimentalist study
and control indeed think of it almost as
an engineering resource so this property
of entanglement should sound strange to
somebody because it means if there's a
way in which the two particles are
linked even if they're very far apart
from each other and that violates the
principle that physicists have held to
be sacred which is locality which is
that influences and forces
travel through space from one point to
another don't act directly jumping over
big regions of space wasn't Einstein
skeptical of entanglement I think I
recalled he had a paper was that the EPR
paper this is the tape I'm referring to
in 1935 yeah where he called it spooky
action at a distance and was really put
the paper out to say there must be
something wrong with quantum mechanics
if this is what it implies and yet as I
understand it and he could correct me on
this if I'm off that modern experimental
physics has shown that the EPR effect is
actually what happens yes now what
happened is that Einstein and his young
collaborators Podolsky and Rosen Boris
Podolsky and Nathan Rosen fashioned an
argument which assumed that there were
only local influences and came to
conclusion that quantum mechanics had to
be incomplete you have an incomplete
description of reality and their
assumption that they're only local
influences was wrong so their conclusion
could not be held but nonetheless the
paper was a breakthrough paper because
it led to the recognition of this
property of entanglement which was then
found and measured by experimentalist to
be real now the next person in the story
is an Irish physicist called John Bell
who was a particle physicist and he came
along in the 1960s and he fashioned an
elementary very easy to formulate and
check and prove theorem that if locality
were true in cases like this where two
particles interact and then separated
then there was a certain constraint on
measured values of certain correlations
and there's no reason to explain it here
to your viewers you could describe he
could derive a certain constraint on
measured values in some experiment and
the assumption was that when the
particles were very far apart that wet
one choose to measure of one of them
doesn't affect what's true about the
other one and if you're a realist and
you believe in locality how could it be
that whether I choose to measure the
or the momentum or something else Oh a
particle that's come over here to my
laboratory shouldn't affect it's obvious
that that shouldn't affect what's true
about a particle that maybe now it's
around somewhere around Mars or Jupiter
and just making this assumption which we
call now Bell locality but I'll prove
this inequality had to be true about the
measured values of certain observables
and then he could do the calculation in
quantum mechanics and show that the
values predicted by quantum mechanics
contradicted the inequality so that
meant that that property was false in
quantum mechanics but the dramatic thing
which was demonstrated a decade later
starting the 1970s is that people could
do the experiment and find that the
inequality was violated in the
experiment so without any reference to
quantum mechanics we have tested this
assumption about locality and it's false
and not just by a little bit it's
dramatically false I think this was big
this is a big story for our listeners is
that realism can include nonlocality
no Jim let me put it to you stronger
realism or non realism nonlocality is
part of nature this experiment doesn't
it doesn't sue many philosophy of nature
it just describes certain correlations
between measurements you might make on a
pair of particles and makes that one
assumption I believe me people have
combed this thing it's a very short
paper there's not much to it the other
assumptions you go into the calculation
or trivial things like probabilities and
numbers between zero and one which you
can try to disbelieve if you want to get
out of it but I think everybody would
agree that this probability means
anything the probability is something to
happen is between zero and one so people
have looked for a loophole people look
for mistakes and it's pretty remarkably
solid at this point those of us have
looked into this as educated layman
have seen the claims that despite the
fact that there appears to be an
instantaneous effect faster than the
speed of light between
entangled particles that are far apart
there is no way to actually send
information faster than the speed of
light is that something you can talk
about yes this goes back to the
randomness you asked me about at the
beginning of the show because if we look
at any one detector for one particle the
outcomes are random it's only when you
look at the correlations of the
statistics that you get by averaging
over many instances of measurements on
these pairs of particles that you see
the observable and constructed that John
Doe was pointing to and see that it
violates the assumption of locality so
because quantum mechanics and quantum
physics as far as we can tell it's
statistical you can send information
faster than light now there are twists
to this because let's go back to the
pilot wave theory
and the pilot wave theory but how does
it agree with the statistics of quantum
mechanics you have to make an assumption
which is that if you make a non sample
of trials as you can do an experiment
over and over again the wave is always
the same wave but you start the particle
different places and different these
different runs and what what you assume
about how you choose the starting points
for the particles and in different runs
you assume that the particles are
distributed in the different runs by a
probability that's related to the square
of the way and that's called borns rule
that was one of the fundamental
principles of quantum mechanics and it
has to apply to the pilot wave theory as
well well there are two points of view
to take to this the traditional one and
one which is argued for by a
contemporary physicist called Antony
Valentini most people including Bohm
and for that matter de bruit to the
Senate understood this question what it
said that's one of the assumptions is
one of the inputs of the theory you just
have to distribute the particles
according to that probability
distribution related to the wave what
you can show is that once you've done
that initially it stays that way so that
as the wave of hours in time and changes
the particles move
guys by the ways they're probably the
distribution always stays related to the
square of the way that's an important
result that tells you that the results
of any experiments are going to agree in
pilot-wave theory and they're in
ordinary quantum mechanics but Antony
Valentini said supposing that you start
off with a probability distribution
different then that related to the
square of the way he just put the
particles in and you know what you want
different from that assumption what
happens then and he called that being
out of equilibrium or out of quantum
equilibrium and the Antony Valentini was
able to prove two remarkable results
about that one of them is that the
system will evolve in time so there
pretty quickly it gets back to the born
rule so even if you start off with a
probability distribution for the initial
particle it's different than the square
of the waves everything somehow
conspires so that pretty soon the
distribution is the same the same one is
like the square of the way that's the
first remarkable result the second one
is that during the period however when
you haven't reached the square of the
wave is the probability distribution you
can send information faster than light
mmm
I have there been a demonstration of
that people have tried not that hard but
people have look for that and so far not
found it it's giving rise to any number
of science fiction books some of them
good some of them well I'm not really
with standing in judgment of science
fiction but science fiction but the
books and ideas of varying quality or
which people aliens or the military or
little high school kids or not so little
high school kids use this to send
information faster than life but it's
standing as an open hypothesis and there
is a well-defined set of experimental
protocols that could demonstrate this if
we had the right apparatus yes ah that's
very interesting I have to keep my eye
on that another realist branch of the
tree is Everett in the multiverse could
you tell us about that so one of the
things that the
Haagen interpretation is that it assumes
that the world is divided into two parts
the quantum system which is what we're
trying to model using quantum mechanical
ideas and mathematics and the outside
rest of the world where the observers in
the measuring instruments in the clocks
and the rest of us live which is assumed
to be described by ordinary that is pre
quantum or Newtonian physics and so poor
and the Copenhagen people require us to
always treat a quantum system as a small
part of the universe and treat the rest
of the universes of quantum mechanics
didn't apply to it but Newtonian physics
still apply that is in our part of the
universe think of Newtonian part there's
no uncertainty everything always has a
definite value independent of how you
measure it and so forth well what are
the questions that became interesting
during the 20th century as all this
proceeded is cosmology because meanwhile
in Stein invented general relativity and
people began to apply it tomorrows of
the whole universe to study things like
the expanding universe that's discovered
by Hubble and that's become quite a big
and successful subject modern cosmology
so what does that have to do with
quantum mechanics well if quantum
mechanics can be applied to a part of
the universe you have a bridge a gap
there that's hard to bridge and so
Johnny wheeler who is one of the great
visionaries of 20th century physics used
to ask himself and his students could
you devise a version of quantum
mechanics as you could apply to the
universe as a whole we wouldn't have to
make the separation into the quantum
world in the classical world you'd have
several have to acknowledge frankly if
the observer is part of the world in the
world is one which is the quantum world
so could you make quantum mechanics
which was the description of the
universities of the whole and this was a
huge challenge and my personal belief is
no to make a theory of the whole
universe we have to go beyond quantum
mechanics
as part of the search for completion of
quantum mechanics but one of John
Wheeler students was Hugh Everett in the
1950s came to a proposal about this and
the proposal was to remove from the
formulation of quantum mechanics
everything about measurement and
probabilities and just leave an equation
by which the wave propagates the wave is
taking the wave side of the wave
particle duality there's a wave equation
called the Schrodinger equation and then
there are other equations that describe
measurement and probabilities for
measurements and ever said supposing we
just take the theory to be given by the
dynamics of the wave when we throw away
the rest can we make sense of that
truncated version of the theory and
because there's no explicit mention of
experimenter an observer because we
maybe apply this to the universe as a
whole now there are two problems with
this there are 30 few problems with it
but one of them is whether you're
supposed to do with the fact that when
you make a measurement sometimes it's
one outcome sometimes is another outcome
sometimes if you have a particle in a
ground state of an atom electrons the
ground state of an atom you ask where is
that electron sometimes it's on one side
of the nuclei sometimes it's in the
other side to declare sometimes it's
close sometimes it's far but there's
always a definite outcome to your asking
the question where is the electron so
how does this theory of the way which
doesn't mention it mention anything
about measurement or probability deal
with that and average proposal was
radical and shocking he said every time
there wasn't the usual quantum mechanics
be a choice like that there would be
different outcomes I'm going to
postulate that the universe splits into
different universes and in each the
universal universe which actually exists
for each possible outcome of the quantum
experiment of every quantum experiment
so every time in nature
the cat could be alive or dead reveal a
particle could be decayed or not return
you these probabilistic things there is
a different version of reality reality
is continually splitting into different
versions or as he called them branches
and we as observers are splitting too
today there are enormous three large
multiple number of copies of each of us
and all of us in all of these different
universities it's completely insane for
the listeners assuming that we're
talking about a truly gargantuan number
of universes you don't like every
radioactive particle whether it when it
splits or doesn't split in any instant
of time is presumably yet another fork
in the multiverse now the story of this
is that it became controversial a lot of
thinking was done about it a Hugh
average himself left physics and went
into defense work doing being a
physicist and engineer for defense
contractors and it apparently quite a
successful career in that domain and
kept up with the debates but never went
back into science but many people have
thought about there are there are
several questions which which you have
to address right away one of them is how
do you account because the probabilities
that we see in ordinary quantum
mechanics when we make from experiments
we see the theory predicts it half the
time the particle is decayed by now and
the other half the time it's not and
that varies as time goes on and more and
more a part of the decayed there's a lot
that quantum mechanics predicts about
probabilities where do they come from
if the Everett proposal is true because
in the average proposal every one of
these outcomes exists not with some
probability but with probability one in
each exists with probability one and the
only question is which to experience on
the branch that this particular version
of you that I'm talking to doesn't seem
to be a contradiction to me I mean if
you go down the branches and you just
happen to go on the branches of white
black white black black white white
that's what you happen to see and
because all of our experiments don't
happen simultaneously I don't see a
contradiction there there's not a
certain contradiction because you still
have to ask the theory where the
particular probabilities in quantum
mechanics for days come from you know
the nature of the branching of an
essentially yes
no one way to say it is that you have to
reproduce this rule that I was telling
you about a few minutes ago so the
probabilities are proportional to the
square of the way which is called borns
rule there are sort of two stages in the
history of this one of them is Everett
who wrote this 1957 and a number of
people since who attempted to make use
of it and and this kind of this is not
in an area where I work directly but I
certainly know many of these people and
admire many of them even if I find the
idea very unsettling and unconvincing
there's a kind of first stage where
people finally realized that ever it
didn't have all the answers and that's
the ever theory as described newspapers
is not adequate to address all the
questions it must and then there's a
group of mainly philosophers although
they're led by one brilliant
iconoclastic physicist David Deutsch was
somebody that I admire enormously even
as I disagree with him about so many
things I think he is a great scientist
and his books are very worth reading
very provocative so David Deutsch and
then a number of philosophers at Oxford
University made a much more
sophisticated version in which they
connected these questions about
probabilities in the Everett world to
questions about how you make decisions
is given probabilistic knowledge of your
circumstance a branch of probability
theory that's been developed and is
applied to in the investment world er in
a number of other projects circumstances
called decision theory so it was David's
brilliant idea to apply decision theory
to this question that is if you were an
observer in an air
world there are no probabilities but you
still have to make bets and what guides
what wisdom guides the bet you make when
you bet how whether which branch you're
gonna be on when where the particle went
left of the particle went right and so
this is a new part of the subject and
there are lots of ins and outs of it so
here's what I regressed for the reader
so I wrote these two stages in the
development of the theory became two
chapters in my book the chapters 10 and
11 and I think I misjudged and if
somebody has tried to read them I freely
confess that I kind of misjudged how
hard these things were and probably we
shouldn't have put them in a book meant
for it as he put it intelligent but
talked to the audience but maybe you you
know the reader can decide in any case
it's a fascinating subject in the end
the answers are unknown that is the
experts themselves are as of this moment
highly divided as to whether real
logical and mathematical sense can be
made of how you pullouts probabilities
from this theory and it's a fascinating
story and it's ongoing
I'm gonna throw out an interesting lunch
conversation I had with Murray gell-mann
once at the Santa Fe Institute that was
one of the joys of being a researcher
there was you got to hang out with
people like Murray and you know just
have random discussions and I went down
the quantum interpretations discussion
with him one day and said hey Murray
what do you think and I realized he's
written on this but he gave me a
shorthand answer which I have not been
able to find him ever putting in writing
which he called the as if many-worlds
interpretation he said you know about
Everett his multiverse and I said yeah
he says imagine Everett is right about
the math but by some magical mechanism
which we do not understand only one of
the worlds actually happens at each such
branch he says that
was his best gut gifts of the best
interpretation out there doesn't say I
never heard him say that either but
Murray did write a number of papers on
the interpretation of quantum mechanics
most of them with Jim Hartle who was a
good friend of his and they espouse
something that they called the
consistent histories interpretation of
quantum mechanics which I suppose is
something like what you just described
it's an average plus roofer when you can
regard the world as real rather than
just a fictional possibility he
certainly seemed to be a real estimate
he would denounce people that remember
him saying once yeah some people say if
you don't look at the moon it's not
really there that's ridiculous the
moon's always been there so he would
certainly seem to have been on the
realist side of your realist
non-realistic I
he was Jim Harlow was more adventurous
in his anti-realism he basically said
realism surrealism we've talked about
other people's theories on the realist
branch Lee what's your program what's
your best ideas about quantum
foundations so Jim I see the problem of
quantum foundations as part and parcel
of the problem of quantum gravity the
problem of how to unify quantum physics
with our understanding of space and time
and gravity which mostly but most of
what we know about that is coming from
Einstein's theory of general relativity
so one way to think about this is
unifying quantum mechanics with general
relativity and to me that's what I mean
by Einstein's unfinished revolution I'm
saying
instigators relativity theory at 1905
for the special theory in there in 1915
ten years later the general theory which
included space and time and gravity and
at the same time in 1905 he instigated
the quantum revolution and I think that
both revolutions are still in progress
and will culminate simultaneously so for
me the
this clue is what we're talking about a
little bit earlier nonlocality
quantum mechanics is describing a world
somehow hidden behind our world in which
space is not fundamental in which
whether two particles interact has
something to do with their history but
not with whether they're near to each
other or far to each other at the moment
in other words entanglement to the
entanglement is more fundamental than
space and so I have a program of
research designed to find the completion
the theory which is the completion both
of our understanding of space and time
and gravity and our theory of quantum
phenomenon and I'm a realist I'm very
very much so so I don't make any
compromises with complementarity or
Copenhagen now I believe three other
things to put everything on the table
one of them is that between space and
time time is really real time is
fundamental time is irreversible the
feelings we have the experience we have
the passage of time from the past to the
present into the future is not an
illusion is not somehow a statistical
illusion is misleading but it's really
how nature is constructed so I'm what is
called sometimes the present is I
believe that what's real and what's true
in the world is the present moment which
is evolving from the past through the
future I'm also a relational list which
is that I follow the philosophy of
Einstein and Mark and going back to some
great philosopher called lightness but
the quantities that physics is
interested in like motion and position
and state are all about relationships
they're about relationships of the
particle or the system we're studying
with the rest of the universe there are
no absolute properties there's no
absolute meaning to where something is
or how it's moving all of these are are
aspects of relationships so I try to
construct a theory that is realist that
is present is that is relation list
and that can give us back in the
appropriate approximation quantum theory
and general relativity so that's kind of
a tall order that that's the world that
I plan it goes that I work for I think
that's interesting because it gives you
a parallax so to speak on the problem
you know people working just in the
quantum world are looking at nuances
there you're looking at it from both
within the quantum world but you're also
looking at it from the the relativistic
large scale at the same time this may
give you a unique way of thinking about
the problem yes I think it gives me a
lot of ingredients and direction I agree
with that I should also say that I have
wonderful company at different stages
this work I've been definitely blessed
to have good collaborators and people
who are incredibly insightful and smart
and provocative in their thinking so I
want to mention them Roberto mangabeira
Unger 14e Marco Polo marina Cortes
Stephon Alexander and a bunch of others
because without them I would really be
nowhere about half my work in this area
is single lots of papers designed by
myself passed very much under the
influence of these and other people and
of course though all the great thinkers
as well now really ever since my career
started during my first postdoc I have
every five or six years published a
paper which was a proposal to make this
relational completion of quantum
mechanics so and there have been a
number of different versions of it they
all concur that space is that
entanglement is primary that non
locality is primary and indeed that
causation and evolution and time are
primary things but the primary
description doesn't include anything
happening in space that things
developing space are a kind of illusion
like temperature and pressure and
thermodynamics their consequences of
looking at the
Zana large and very average and
coarse-grained sense and that if you
look specifically at what is really
happening there's no there's no space
there's just events and causes of events
and now as I recall from your previous
book time reborn I was really taken with
that book some time back and as I recall
one of the predictions you made or
enough predictions the right word maybe
it's a prediction a implication of your
thinking was that this relational list
geometry of what we call space but you
have a different metaphor if your
theories are correct we should find
non-local connections you know if we
think of space it's a very very fine
grid with neighbors kind of like a
screen in your window if I read it right
if I treated it correctly you're saying
there was like a thread that would come
up off the screen go three-quarters the
way over the screen and come down on a
new intersection and provide a shortcut
across space yes this is an idea we do
those with photinia Marco Polo and she
called it the disordering of locality
yeah and I thought that was just Wow
and it also struck me that maybe there
was an experimental way to see if that
was true well maybe and we spend some
time on enough thinking about that it
was one paper that I wrote with the
student in which we used these non-local
connections as part of the dark energy
the dark energy being this mystery in
cosmology of a substance that seems to
fill the universe and behave like an
energy that's distributed throughout the
universe the kind of energy of empty
space and there are other consequences
that we've thought about from time to
time
version of these ideas that I'm engaged
in now so as I said mostly I've been
working on quantum gravity and
occasionally other questions but every
five or so years I went back and thought
about these problems in quantum
foundations and got a little further I
knew a little more and had a little
different toolkit and developed a
different proposal a different version
of this theory that that I described the
present one the present version is
called the causal theory of use and it's
kind of culmination of three different
ideas developed with different people
one of them is the theory of the
universe is based on causal evolution
and we call it the energetic causal set
models that we developed with Marina
Cortez another is an idea called
relative locality in which there's a
kind of relativity principle that
applies to whether something is local or
not that we developed with several
friends and colleagues
neurontin friend al Giovanni M you know
Camellia and your AK Alaska Glickman and
other people who contributed to in the
last is an approach to what is quantum
mechanics to reinventing quantum physics
based on some very different assumptions
that I called the real ensemble
formulation that I've been developing
for about six or seven years and the
three of these things but you I'm just
telling you the names of things put
together resulting in the theory called
the causal theory of views that I'm
quite I've published one paper about and
I'm quite struck with it I'm wrestling
with now but I managed to show that
there are some approximations to this
theory they can be construct as one of
which gives back ordinary quantum
mechanics and I'm working on more
sophisticated of things that have to be
true very very interesting I got so many
other topics here on my questions Leslie
but let's jump to a one a little further
afield and
that listener regular listeners of the
podcast will be familiar with I'd love
to hear your thoughts on the Fermi
paradox and for the new listener the
Fermi paradox references a discussion
that happened at the lunch tables back
at Los Alamos during World War two and
they're working on the atomic bomb and a
bunch of young smart guys were sitting
around debating how many intelligent
civilizations must there be in the
universe and they would take some
assumptions about how often life evolved
how often life became intelligent etc
and they were roughly came to a
conclusion that there had to be hundreds
of thousands of intelligent species in
the universe and then Enrico Fermi one
of the most distinguished physicists at
Los Alamos came over to the lunch table
and said okay but where are they and
since then this question this Fermi
paradox has been something that a number
of people have been thinking about and
it you know it's a really important and
deep question and sort of at the
broadest level there's two forks
we've been looking now for 70 years 60
or 70 years for signs of other
intelligent life in the universe
listening on radio telescopes looking
for possible artifacts looking for non
life of a different sort than our own
life in the ocean that's a recent
attempt and so far it all comes back
zero everything we can see in the
universe appears to us at least to be
dead and there's two basic Forks on that
fact one is that there are none that we
are for whatever reason the only
advanced technological intelligence
society at least in our galaxy but then
there's the second branch which says no
they're out there but for various
reasons we can't see them either they
don't want us to see them or their
technology and their world is evolved in
a direction such that they don't give
off the kind of science and artifacts
that we might see later you have some
thoughts on the Fermi paradox
hi I have really just one thought which
was and I put in my first book life of
the cosmos which is that we should
introduce a time scale and presume that
there is a civilization out there and
they do explore they are able to travel
at not the speed of light but maybe a
thousand seven hundred the speed of
light and they do come by from time to
time and look and see if intelligent
life has sprouted and where intelligent
life is likely to sprout and the
question I asked is first question I
asked is what's the time period under
which we can expect them to check back
and I thought a few hundred million
years and that's also because that's how
long it would take life to evolve from
say a stage of just prokaryotes in the
ocean in primitive ocean to more
sophisticated eukaryotes and
multicellular creatures and you'd only
have to check back every few hundred
million years to get an idea of what was
brewing so to speak and also how long it
would take to cross the galaxy had a
fraction of the speed of life figured
into that so anyway I said so something
between ten and a hundred a few hundred
million years then the second question I
asked coming from that is let's put
ourselves in their situation they're
here on a primitive earth they see maybe
some life in the ocean maybe some plants
maybe even some very primitive land
animals and they aren't gonna come back
every few hundred million years but just
in case some intelligent life develops
quickly unexpectedly before that time or
maybe intelligent life visits from
somewhere else which is also possible
well they would like to leave a message
where would they leave a message that
could last a hundred million years so
that if any intelligent life evolved who
came by
they could leave a record of how to get
in touch and I thought about that and
discussed it with a few friends and the
conclusion I came to is that there's
only one reliable place they could leave
it and that's in the junk DNA you have
whatever species they find in the
mitochondrial DNA because that doesn't
undergo sexual division and selection so
I suggested and I don't know if anybody
ever took this up going through the junk
DNA or the mitochondrial DNA of a number
of species looking for artificial
messages or patterns of signals patterns
of the car genetic code that would be
through its formal structure unlikely to
have been generated naturally by natural
selection wouldn't that signal have been
scrambled by now by mutations maybe but
there's a mutation rate and that's why
mitochondrial DNA the mutation rate is
all that matters in the rate here of DNA
of course it's scrambled every
generation sexually yeah and also by
things like crossover would sir you know
above and beyond the normal sexual
reproduction
I would agree mitochondria be in the
right place would have to look and see
what the base rate mutation is on base
pairs and mitochondrial DNA and then of
course all many of those likely to be
fatal because the mitochondria DNA it's
small and it's very key to our
metabolism but anyway that's an
interesting idea for any biochemists out
there to pick up Lee's idea and run with
it
trait I haven't Jim I haven't gone back
and thought about it much since that
book which was 1997 let me ask you about
another one of your ideas from the past
the idea that our universe is a child of
a previous universe which is a child of
a previous universe universe is bloomed
essentially out of the backside of black
holes in their previous universe with a
small jiggling of the laws of physics
and that there's this then tree of
universes and those universes which have
lots of black holes have lots of
children and so universes
and in the artifice I call that book you
actually suggested there was some
counterfactuals that might well soon be
discovered in terms was it curvature of
the universe I don't remember but anyway
if you could update us on the status of
that theory I mean whether there's been
any new information that would rule that
one in or out so that theory I call
cosmological natural selection and it
was the subject of my first book life of
the cosmos
there isn't much new unfortunately I'm
sorry to say but the important statement
is that I made based on that theory in
1992 two predictions one of them is that
the heaviest possible neutron star would
be no heavier than twice the mass of the
Sun the so called upper mass limit for
neutron stars and the other has to do
with the hypothesis of inflation that
there's a huge expansion very early in
the universe that gives new universes
ultimate size and shape and so forth and
the prediction from my theory for
inflation is that only the simplest
possible model of inflation so-called
single field single parameter inflation
could be correct and if there was a
measurement of the details of the
fluctuations in the microwave background
or in the distribution of galaxies or in
the other ways that we can measure the
early state of the universe they would
have to be explained by that kind of
inflation theory with one field in one
parameter and so far both of those
predictions hold up although I should
say that there are a few observations of
neutron stars that come in with a higher
mass as the central value they have
large error bars and in all the cases in
which michonne star masses are well
measured there at most one point nine
seven times the mass of the Sun so they
come very close to violating the bound
but don't yet violated okay that's
interesting so you were the theory is
still alive hasn't been clearly
falsified
then there's no new evidence to support
it either is that a fair way to describe
it yes way the way that I saw this
theory is not III didn't make a big bed
personally that the theory would be
correct that the assumptions that its
cosmological natural selection makes did
you summarize would be correct but it
demonstrated something which I think is
very important which is that a theory of
framework in which laws can evolve over
time and remember I believe the time is
real and fundamental has greater
empirical success in the sense of makes
more falsifiable predictions then the
theory that assumes that the laws are
eternal and fixed it's also somehow I
don't know what I would call it
encouraging you know that the future is
not laplacian yes I feel that way I
can't put my finger on it scientifically
but just as a human being I feel better
about living in that kind of a universe
doesn't mean that's the kind of level
universe we live in but I hope we are
this we're talking about results with
respect to theory going back to our
quantum foundations what is the state of
knowledge that helps us think between
different quantum approaches both things
that have are known now or probably more
interestingly experiments that could be
run relatively soon or data that is
likely to be gathered from our
explorations of the universe that might
throw some light on which of these many
views of quantum mechanics are more
right than the others or that you're
right none of them are right we have to
rethink the thing what what is the
factual and experimental environment for
thinking about these theories right now
it's fabulous it's fabulous environment
let me mention two kinds of experiments
which are in different ways are testing
the foundations of quantum mechanics
there's a proposal by Roger Penrose and
a number of other people that the way if
a part of the wave-particle duality the
so-called wavefunction from time to time
spontaneously collapses now to give you
some background for this one of the
assumptions of the second part of
quantum mechanics I described that has
to do with measurement is that if you
have a wavefunction which is spread out
over a large area and you try to observe
the position of the particle you will
discover the particle is at some
position and from then on the
wavefunction collapses to begin growth
again from a concentration at that point
where the particle was found and that
collapsed the wavefunction or the
projection postulate is called by von
Neumann is a separate postulate but it's
part of the postulates of quantum
mechanics now the Orthodox
interpretation of quantum mechanics
tells us that this happens whenever we
make a measurement but then that makes
it very observer dependent and intention
and knowledge dependent Roger Penrose
said maybe there's some real physical
reason that tells the wavefunction to
collapse there's some criteria that
maybe is expressed in an equation which
brings about the collapse of the
wavefunction
and he hypothesized that this had to do
with when gravity would be measurable
that is if you imagine you have
something like the Schrodinger card
where the cat is either alive or dead if
there became a separation between the
live in the dead cat large enough to
make a measurable difference in the
gravitational field then that would
trigger this process of wavefunction
collapse according to Roger Penrose and
the sensitivity to do that experiment in
other words to see a new quantum effect
which is not part of the standard theory
coming from trying to locate a mass
which is a big enough mass that is could
affect the geometry of space and time
general relativity is just about
testable right now and there are in the
last year a number of papers by several
different research groups I think all in
Europe describing concrete plans to do
such an experiment and that's extremely
exciting the other thing that's
extremely exciting to me is the growth
of in the size of the molecule that we
can treat as entangled see I'm described
entanglement as these correlations or
shared properties but entanglement has
an enemy which is noise random thermal
noise is coming from the fact that
everything is randomly in motion because
everything is at some temperature and in
order to see the effects of entanglement
you have to somehow kill the effects of
the random noise that permeates
everywhere and people are learning to do
this and as they do it the size of the
quantum system which can be studied with
respect to entanglement and this related
properties gives up a little bit and
there are larger and larger systems of
entangled quantum states that are being
produced in the laboratory and this is
very exciting because it seems to me in
the kind of theories that I make if it's
a place of quantum mechanics breaks down
it's this regime where we start to
describe entangled States have a large
number of particles joined together not
just to is in the
einstein-podolsky-rosen argument but 10
or 20 I presume the escalating work in
quantum computing will be focusing on
some of these from an engineering
perspective if not from a scientific one
and might well develop some technologies
to be able to see more deeply into
questions of this sort well I'd like to
thank you Lee I know you have to go this
has been a an amazingly wonderful
conversation everything I was hoping it
would be and more and I would encourage
our listeners to go out and look under
lease
in Amazon and take a look at some of his
books they're all interesting and this
has been great thank you Sam thank you
very much for the opportunity production
services and audio editing by Stanton
Media Lab music by Tom Muller at modern
space music.com
[Music]